Guide to the Khalil Abdulkhabir photographs of the Dar-ul-Islam movement 2020.002
Brooklyn Historical Society
Khalil Abdulkhabir photographs of the Dar-ul-Islam movement
1972-1977
Brooklyn Historical Society
Abdulkhabir, Khalil
2020.002
7.52 Megabytes in 16 digital photographic images in jpeg format.
The Khalil Abdulkhabir photographs of the Dar-ul-Islam movement collection comprises sixteen digital photographic images taken by Khalil Abdulkhabir documenting the activities of Brooklyn's Dar-ul-Islam community in the 1970s. The Dar-ul-Islam, known as "the Dar", was one of the first and most significant grassroots movements established by African-American Sunni Muslims in America. The Brooklyn Dar community was focused around the Yasin Mosque, at 52 Herkimer Place in Bedford-Stuyvesant.
Disk Archived Digital Assets:\!Web
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Kamila Barbour, daughter of Khalil Abdulkhabir, 2020.
Scope and Contents
This Khalil Abdulkhabir photographs of the Dar-ul-Islam movement collection comprises sixteen digital photographs, primarily black and white, of Dar-ul-Islam activities, taken by Khalil Abdulkhabir between 1972 and 1977. The Dar-ul-Islam, known as "the Dar", was one of the first and most significant grassroots movements established by African-American Sunni Muslims in America. The Bedford-Stuyvesant Dar community was focused around the Yasin Mosque, at 52 Herkimer Place. The photographer, Khalil Abdulkhabir, discovered photography during his work with Youth in Action, an anti-poverty program in Brooklyn, NY. He devoted his time to photography projects designed to educate and motivate youth in the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood. Abdulkhabir and his wife Tunura raised seven children in the Dar and he currently resides in Syracuse, NY.
Related Materials
Muslims in Brooklyn oral histories (2018.006)
Arrangement
Items are arranged by date.
Other Finding Aids
Item-level description and images are available for searching via PastPerfect Online.
Muslims |z New York (State) |z New York; Black Muslims; Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); African Americans; Photography |z New York (State) |z New York; Halal food -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Islamic religious education -- United States; Religious institutions |z New York (State) |z New York; Religious education of children |z New York (State) |z New York; Mosques -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Photographers |z New York (State) |z New York; Festivals |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Dar-ul-Islam Movement
- Brother from Yasin Mosque hands out dawa literature at street bazaar, Nostrand Ave and Fulton Street, 1972 (Disk Archived Digital Assets:\!Web)
- Congresswoman Shirley Chisholm visits the Dar-ul-Miska table at a street festival on Fulton Street, 1972 (Disk Archived Digital Assets:\!Web)
- Brother from Yasin Mosque and Nation of Islam brother, Nostrand Ave and Fulton Street, 1973 (Disk Archived Digital Assets:\!Web)
- Bazaar merchant at the Islamic Center of Washington, 1973 (Disk Archived Digital Assets:\!Web)
- Members from affiliated Dar mosques in the courtyard of the Islamic Center of Washington, 1973 (Disk Archived Digital Assets:\!Web)
- Jawwala Scouts Boy Scout Troop 599 asking for donations at the Islamic Center of Washington, 1973 (Disk Archived Digital Assets:\!Web)
- Rad members posing across the street from Yasin Mosque, 1973 (Disk Archived Digital Assets:\!Web)
- Ministers from Yasin Mosque, members of the Muslim Students Association and Association of Muslim Social Scientists at a conference in Painted Post, NY, 1973 (Disk Archived Digital Assets:\!Web)
- Conference speaker addressing attendees, Painted Post, NY, 1973 (Disk Archived Digital Assets:\!Web)
- Elder Somali traveler and editor of Jihad-ul-Akbar magazine conversing in Brooklyn Botanic Garden, 1974 (Disk Archived Digital Assets:\!Web)
- Jawwala Scouts in racing competition at Ten Mile River Scout Camp, Catskills, NY, 1974 (Disk Archived Digital Assets:\!Web)
- Inspecting meat at The Halal Meat Store, 143 Court Street, 1975 (Disk Archived Digital Assets:\!Web)
- Teacher instructing Madrassah-tush-Shaheedain students in a satellite building on Bedford Ave and Jefferson Street, 1975 (Disk Archived Digital Assets:\!Web)
- Teacher from Madrassah-tush-Shaheedain with children outside Yasin Mosque, 1975 (Disk Archived Digital Assets:\!Web)
- Families celebrating Eid Prayer at Restoration Center, 1368 Fulton Street, 1977 (Disk Archived Digital Assets:\!Web)
- Studio test shot at Reflection Studios, 93 Putnam Avenue, 1977 (Disk Archived Digital Assets:\!Web)